<html>
<head>
<title>About the Collection : Photographic Archive : The
University of Chicago</title>
</head>
<body>

<div class="widecolumn">

<a href="db.xqy?one=apf2-06545.xml">
<img alt="" id="illustrationlarge" src="graphics/apf2-06545.jpg"/>
</a>

<h1>About the Collection</h1>

<p>The Photographic Archive digital collection presents digital
facsimiles of original documentary images in the University of Chicago
Archives. The original images are organized into five broad topical
series, described as follows:</p>

<h2 style="clear: right;">Series I: Individuals and Groups</h2>

<p>Photographs of individuals currently or formerly affiliated with the
University of Chicago, principally Trustees, administrators, faculty
members, staff, donors, and alumni; photographs of academic and
administrative groups associated with the University of Chicago and its
predecessors and affiliates, including Old University of Chicago classes,
University of Chicago academic departments, and degree-granting
interdisciplinary academic committees.</p>

<h2>Series II: Buildings and Grounds</h2>

<p>Photographs of buildings, campus plans, landscaping, and campus views of
the University of Chicago and its predecessor and affiliate institutions;
the Chicago neighborhoods of Hyde Park, Kenwood, and Woodlawn; the Hyde
Park-Kenwood urban renewal project; and city parks near the campus,
including Jackson Park, Washington Park, and other components of the South
Parks system; selected photographs of the South Side and central areas of
the city of Chicago.</p>

<h2>Series III: Events</h2>

<p>Photographs of academic, public, and historical events associated with the
history of the University of Chicago and its predecessors and affiliates;
photographs of alumni activities, academic ceremonies, exhibitions, faculty
activities, inaugurations, alumni reunions, visits to campus of notable
individuals, activities associated with World War I and World War II, and
the World's Columbian Exposition of 1893.</p>

<h2>Series IV: Student Activities</h2>

<p>Photographs of formal and informal student activities on the University of
Chicago campus, including academic classes, laboratories, and seminars;
men's fraternities and women's social clubs; athletic competitions and
individual sports activities in candid views; general recreational
activities; academic registration and orientation programs; residence halls
and housing; and theatrical groups and dramatic productions.</p>

<h2>Series V: Sports</h2>

<p>Posed photographs of individual student athletes and posed group
photographs of athletic teams of the University of Chicago and University
High School; photographs representing men's and women's sports including
baseball, basketball, cross-country, fencing, field hockey, football, golf,
gymnastics, ice hockey, polo, soccer, swimming, tennis, track, water polo,
weight-lifting, and wrestling.</p>

<h2>Series VI:  Yerkes</h2>

<p>Among the most significant visual materials in the Yerkes collection are
more than 4,800 documentary photographs.  These depict the construction of
the main observatory building and the installation of instruments, the work
of astronomers and staff, astronomical expeditions to sites including
Sumatra and Catalina Island, and important visitors, among them Albert
Einstein.</p>

<h2>Series VII: Chicago Maroon</h2>

<p>Photographs from the Chicago Maroon, the independent U of C student
newspaper, documenting campus social life, student organizations,
meetings, rallies, and athletics.</p>

<h2>Guide to the Photographic Archive</h2>

<p>A guide to the scope and arrangement of the original photographs in the
Photographic Archive is available on the Special Collections
Research Center web site:</p>

<p>Guide to the Photographic Archive:<br/>
<a href="http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/findaid/photofiles/">
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/findaid/photofiles/</a></p>

<h2>View Materials from the Collection</h2>

<p>The original photographs in the Photographic Archive, along with
additional historical photographs located in other archival and manuscript
collections, are available for consultation by researchers in the Special
Collections Research Center.</p>

<p>Special Collections Research Center<br/>
University of Chicago Library<br/>
1100 E. 57th Street<br/>
Chicago, Illinois 60637<br/>
Fax: (773) 702-3728</p>
<p><a href="http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/ask/SCRC.html">Contact the
Special Collections Research Center</a>.</p>

</div>

</body>
</html>
