<record>
  <titleSeries>Series II: Buildings and Grounds</titleSeries>
  <titleName>Atomic Pile</titleName>
  <titleTypeName>Stagg Field (Old)</titleTypeName>
  <identifierScanNumber>apf2-00504</identifierScanNumber>
  <titlePhotoSequenceNumber>4</titlePhotoSequenceNumber>
  <alternateTitle1>Metallurgical Laboratory, Manhattan Engineer District</alternateTitle1>
  <dateBuildingGroundsCreated>1942</dateBuildingGroundsCreated>
  <datePhotographCreated>1942-12-02</datePhotographCreated>
  <creatorPhotographer>Argonne National Laboratory</creatorPhotographer>
  <description>Photograph of a model showing the first nuclear reactor erected in 1942 in a squash court in the West Stands of Stagg Field at the University of Chicago. On December 2, 1942 (as depicted here), a group of scientists under the direction of Enrico Fermi achieved the first self-sustaining chain reaction and thereby initiated the controlled release of nuclear energy. Fermi and his colleagues were assembled on the balcony to the right to observe the instruments recording the neutron intensity in the pile. After 28 minutes the operators to the right of the reactor pushed in a cadmium control rod called zip and ended the world's first chain reaction to be achieved by man. The reactor in the left foreground contained alternate layers of dead graphite containing uranium metal and uranium oxide. The completed reactor contained 57 layers which was about one layer beyond the critical stage.</description>
  <subject1>Models (Representations)</subject1>
  <subject2>Nuclear reactors</subject2>
  <subject3>Science rooms and equipment</subject3>
  <coverageSpatial2>University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois</coverageSpatial2>
  <coverageSpatial3>CH01</coverageSpatial3>
  <formatOriginalMedium>Photographic prints</formatOriginalMedium>
  <formatOriginalExtent>17.9 x 24.0 cm</formatOriginalExtent>
  <format>image/jpeg</format>
  <type>Image</type>
  <source>Archival Photographic Files</source>
  <relationIsPartOf>Archival Photofiles</relationIsPartOf>
  <publisher>University of Chicago Library, Special Collections Research Center</publisher>
  <identiferBarcode>50738731</identiferBarcode>
  <photoTotalCopies>3</photoTotalCopies>
  <noteGeneral>Photographer's stamp. Stamp: Released for publication.  Stamp: Please return to the University of Chicago Office of Press Relations.  University of Chicago Archives stamp.</noteGeneral>
  <makerPhotographicNumber>201-4152</makerPhotographicNumber>
  <recordNumber>504</recordNumber>
</record>
